<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King and Queen, at White-Hall, in November 1692 by William Jane ...</title>
            <author>Jane, William, 1645-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3438</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12892120</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12892120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 716:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King and Queen, at White-Hall, in November 1692 by William Jane ...</title>
                  <author>Jane, William, 1645-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the Theater for Thomas Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [Oxfordshire] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXIX, 106 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95120:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Before the King &amp; Queen, AT <hi>WHITE-HALL, In November</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM JANE,</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by their MAJESTIES Command.</p>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed at the THEATER, for <hi>Thomas Bennet</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard, <hi>London</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95120:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95120:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. CXIX. 106.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have ſworn, and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous Judgments.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpends this whole Pſalm, partly in recounting his own mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, partly in magnifying the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and meditation of God's Law, as the greateſt comfort, and refreſhment, that he met with in all his diſtreſſes, and perſecutions. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges throughout upon the excellency, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and advantages thereof, that the true and only felicity of man attainable in this life depends upon it, and that ſo great was the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, ſo chearful the reflections he derived from it, that all the preſſures and afflictions of the world were not able to make him miſerable. He frequently declares the high eſteem, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, that he had for it, his ſtedfaſt reſolutions to continue, and perſevere in the obſervance of it, together with a conſtant intermixture of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95120:3"/>earneſt and fervent Prayers for Gods Grace, and aſſiſtance to enable him ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>In this verſe we have a noble expreſſion, of an Holy and Couragious reſolution, flowing from the conviction of his Judgment, and deeply root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his heart, <hi>I have ſworn, and I will perform it,</hi> or as the other tranſlation has it, <hi>I have ſworn, and am steadfaſtly purpoſed to keep thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments.</hi> i. e. By my admiſſion into the number of thy people I am entered into a ſolemn Sacramental Covenant to perform obedience to thy Commands,<note place="margin">Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond in loc.</note> I do now acknowledge my ſelf indiſpenſably engaged to thy Service, and withal renew my vows, and reſolutions never to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it.</p>
            <p>The only inference I ſhall make from the words at preſent ſhall be only to ſhew, of what great uſe, benefit, and advantage it is in the buſineſs of religion to lay down fixed, and ſteady reſolutions to undertake it, and to purſue the deſigns of it with the whole bent, and bias of the Soul. And thus we find the Saints in Scripture have uſually devoted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſervice of their God. Thus <hi>David</hi> in another place, <hi>my heart is fixed O God my heart is fixed, Pſ.</hi> 57.7. Thus <hi>Mattathias</hi> 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Tho all the Nations under the Kings Dominions ſhall fall every one from the Religion of their Fathers, yet will I and my ſons and my
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95120:3"/>brethren walk in the Covenant of our Fathers.</hi> Thus thoſe in <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Come let us joyn our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetual Covenant, that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> And this <hi>Barnabas</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends to the Converts at <hi>Antioch Acts</hi> 11. 23. <hi>that with full purpoſe of heart they would cleave unto the Lord.</hi> A certain velleity, a languid and incomplete will, ſome zealous pang of devotion, may be diſcern'd in <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Herod, Balaam</hi> and <hi>Agrippa;</hi> I am <hi>almoſt perſwaded to be a Christian,</hi> ſays one, and <hi>O that I might dye the death of the righteous,</hi> ſays another; but they were ſtill deſtitute of the true foundation of religion, a ſtrong, firm, and well bottomed reſolution; they had not wrought their hearts to the Pſalmiſts concluſion, <hi>I have ſworn, and am steadfastly purpoſed to keep thy righteous Judgments.</hi> In diſcourſing of this point I ſhall ſhew</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> What is required to the forming a firm and ſettled reſolution,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly</hi> The great moment and importance of ſuch a reſolution in the buſineſs of religion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And 1. of the Firſt of theſe, what is required to the forming a firm and ſettled reſolution. And here firſt it is requiſite that it be the reſult and iſſue of a mature, and ſerious delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Now deliberation is an act or exerciſe of the practical Judgment, or underſtanding,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95120:4"/>employ'd and ſet on work by the will to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and debate the proper means conducible to the end, together with a due weighing and bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing the ſeveral conveniencies, and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies that attend them. This is the work of deliberation in general, and is of very great moment throughout all the actions of our lives.</p>
            <p>In the preſent Caſe it is a thorow, and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial consideration of the Duties, and difficulties of Religion, the pleasures of ſin for a ſeaſon, and the bitterneſs of them in the event, and iſſue; a due comparing of rewards and puniſhments, the preſent, and the future, the ſweetneſs of a good Conſcience, and the torments of a bad, the beauties of virtue, and the deformity of ſin, the ſhortneſs of time, and the length of Eternity: till upon a fair repreſentation of the whole Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of things to our own minds, we have at length brought the debate to this determination, that all the advantage lies on the ſide of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; that the reward of obedience has infinitly more weight to perſwade, than all the hardſhips we muſt grapple with have to diſhearten, and diſcourage us; that there is no proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a moment and eternity; and that all the pleaſures, profits, and honours of the World are of no account at all, when they are laid in the ballance with the everlaſting concerns of our immortal Souls.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95120:4"/>
            <p>This method of the workings of our own minds in forming a ſetled reſolution, Divines have very fitly repreſented by <hi>Joſhuas</hi> dealing with the Children of <hi>Iſrael Joſ.</hi> 24. where he ſummons the people together, and plainly ſets before them the great obligations they lay under to forſake all ſtrange Gods, and faithfully adhere to the Worſhip and Service of the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> He repreſents to them on the one hand, what great things God had done for them, and what greater things he would ſtill doe, if they continued ſteadfaſt in his Covenant. On the other hand he acquaints them with the difficulty of God's Service, the accurate purity, and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which was required for the performance <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>Ye cannot ſerve the Lord, for he is an Holy God.</hi> To this he adds the dreadful Judgments, he would bring upon them in caſe they ſhould tranſgreſs his Covenant, and goe and ſerve o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods, <hi>for he is a jealous God, he will not pardon your tranſgreſsions, nor your ſins</hi> And at laſt after a great many arguments to this purpoſe, and thoſe repeated and inculcated to make the ſtronger impreſſion upon their minds, he refers the matter to their own choice <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>If it ſeem evil unto you to ſerve the Lord, chooſe you this day, whom you will ſerve.</hi> Not that he hereby ſet them perfectly at liberty, as if it were a matter indifferent, whether they ſerv'd God, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95120:5"/>Idols. For his whole deſign had bin hitherto to confirm them, and their poſterity for ever in the worſhip of the true God, and in Caſe they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from it, he would never have ſuffer'd their Apoſtacy to go unpuniſhed. In the words therefore he eloquently inſinuates to them the groſs inequality of the Compariſon, that being ſtir'd up with indignation at ſo vile a choice, as the preferring dumb Idols before the living God, they might the more eaſily, and of their own accord yield an explicit conſent to his propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, totally renounce, and deteſt all falſe worſhip, and adhere to the true Religion with their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vigor and reſolution. And this effect it had upon them <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſay they, <hi>that we ſhould forſake the Lord to ſerve other Gods,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Nay but we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Whereupon, for the greater ſolemnity of the whole tranſaction, <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſets up a ſtone as a memorial to them of the obligations they lay under, and alſo a teſtimony againſt them, if ever they fell off from ſuch a deliberate reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And ſurely whoever undertakes the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of religion, will be ſenſible in a little time, that it required, and needed the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and ſerious deliberation. He will ſoon find it to be an enterprize, that will engage his whole ſtrength and all his powers for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95120:5"/>of it, that it is a work of difficulty, as well as importance, and accordingly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in Scripture under the harſh names of Mortification, and Crucifixion; that it is a ſtrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to enter into <hi>the ſtraight Gate</hi> and <hi>walking in the narrow way</hi> the ſubduing our moſt forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inclinations, <hi>the cutting off a right hand, and the plucking out a right eye,</hi> an utter deteſting of the deareſt, cloſeſt, and moſt affectionate luſts, and the denying our ſelves ſome of the moſt pleaſant gratifications of fleſh, and blood.</p>
            <p>He will quickly experience the frailty, fickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and inconſtancy of his will, the ſubtilty of Satan, the deceitfulneſs of ſin, and the treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and falſhood of his own heart, the ſnares that are laid for him, the dangers that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round him, the enemies that lye in wait for him, the temptations from within, and from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that are by one means or other alwaies thruſting him upon his ruin.</p>
            <p>And when he has but ſlightly conſidered this, he will need no argument to convince him, that all his moſt ſpecious and glittering reſolutions, will quickly vaniſh and come to nothing, unleſs they are founded in a deep ſenſe of the importance of the duty, of the motives, and arguments to embrace it, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the labour he muſt undergoe, the delays he muſt ſuſtain, and the diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95120:6"/>he muſt meet with in the diſcharge of it. The want hereof is the true, and immediate Cauſe of moſt of thoſe ſhameful Apoſtacys, which have cauſed the enemies of God to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme, and made the way of truth to be evil ſpoken of, when men <hi>beginning in the ſpirit, have ended in the fleſh, and after they have known the way of righteouſneſs turn'd from the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment delivered unto them.</hi> Many there are, that are ſometimes in a good mood, in a fit of devotion, when their hearts are warm'd with ſome affectionate diſcourſe, when they are ſurprized with ſome ſad accident or diſaſter, which diſappoints them of the pleaſure that they expected from iniquity, or when God lays ſiege to them by Sickneſs, or ſome other pinching affliction, ſo that the proviſions of luſt have loſt their reliſh with them for the preſent, and the calamity has embitter'd the pleaſantneſs of the temptation. In this caſe it is very uſual with men to be very liberal in their promiſes, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and reſolutions. But when the fit is over, when Gods hand is taken off, and the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſin grow ſtrong enough to preſent themſelves again, they unravel all their former vows, the heart returns to its old byas, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the approach of the next temptation, their <hi>goodneſs vaniſhes like a morning Cloud, and like the early Dew, it paſseth away.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95120:6"/>
            <p>When <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> laid Siege againſt <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem Jer.</hi> 34. the <hi>Jews</hi> made a ſolemn Covenant with the Lord to ſet free their ſervants, but no ſooner had the King removed his ſiege, but they retracted, and repealed their vows, and brought their ſervants back again into their former bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon hereof is plain. For in ſuch a Caſe the motive of their reſolution is not ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate to the matter they reſolve upon, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is too narrow for the ſuperſtructure, and where the principle is particular and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, it can never be a ſufficient ground of a general, and conſtant reſolution. A reſolution that ariſes from the ſenſe of a preſent evil, or the fear of an approaching danger, will ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily laſt no longer, than the calamity that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned it. And ſo as mens fears abate their virtuous reſolutions fall off together with them, ſince that ſhort, and tranſient principle, which firſt gave them life, is no longer able to ſupport them. For there can be no more ſtrength in the concluſion than in the premiſes, and as their motives change, their reſolutions muſt change too. No wonder therefore if the temta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions return as ſtrong as ever, and prevail as much againſt the reſolution, as ever the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion prevailed againſt the ſin.</p>
            <p>And this is uſually the fatal iſſue of all thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95120:7"/>other haſty light, vain, and unſettled purpoſes of men, which ariſe from heat, or paſſion, or a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tranſport of zeal, or any the like principle, which is not commenſurate to the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and extent of their duty. The principles are weak, and wavering, and ſo can beget no other, than faint, and floating reſolutions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews Jo.</hi> 6.15. upon the ſight of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viors miracles were of a ſudden ſo highly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with love to him, that they reſolv'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould hinder them, but they would e'en take him by force, and make him a King. And yet at another time, when the Phariſees, who knew well enough how to doe it, had ſlily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated into their pliable, and unreſolv'd affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they cryed out againſt him as againſt a ſlave <hi>Crucify him, Crucify him,</hi> we have <hi>no King but Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then is the difference between reaſon and paſſion in forming a good purpoſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. The former does not prevent or anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate, but ſlowly follows, and attends the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Counſels of the mind; it firſt brings the matter to a grave, and calm deliberation, and thence wiſely, and ſedately proceeds to action, and execution. But the other is impatient of ſerious thinking, as being a tedious, and irkſome task, and ſo ſetting forward too ſpeedily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Counſel, uſually comes off too cowardly without Courage.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95120:7"/>
            <p>This is that temper, which old <hi>Jacob</hi> reproves in <hi>Reuben</hi> his firſt-born <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.4. <hi>Unſtable as water,</hi> which ſome render raſh, and haſty, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers light, and inconſtant; and the one is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily a conſequent of the other, and therefore he could <hi>not excell,</hi> not only in the number of his tribe <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.6. but neither in valour, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or any excellent atchievement. The ſame is taxt by <hi>Solomon Pro.</hi> 14.29. <hi>he that is hasty of Spirit exalteth folly.</hi> i.e. he makes his folly manifeſt to the world by raſhly adventuring upon that, which when it comes to tryal, he is not able to go through with. They that are the moſt forward and bold in an undertaking, are often found to fall off moſt ſhamefully in the encounter, and the greateſt boaſters before a danger are commonly very timerous or at leaſt inconſtant, when it comes.</p>
            <p>We have a ſad example of this in no leſs a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than <hi>St. Peter.</hi> How confident was, he in proteſting, and promiſing and reſolving that he would ſtick to Chriſt even to the death. A three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold raſhneſs ſome have obſerved in his behaviour in that buſineſs: he oppoſed himſelf to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors forewarning him of his fall. He prefer'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf indiſcreetly before the reſt of his fellow Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and he took the matter wholly upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as that which he thought himſelf upon his own ſtrength to be well enough able to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95120:8"/>for. <hi>Though all ſhould be offended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thee, yet would not I. I will never deny thee: though I dye for it. I will lay down my life for thy ſake. I am ready to go with thee unto priſon and unto death. Matt.</hi> 26.21. <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.38. And what more pregnant teſtimony than this of his love to Chriſt, and reſolution to adhere to him? <hi>Greater love than this,</hi> in the Apoſtles Judgment, <hi>no man hath, than to lay down his life for his friend.</hi> And this <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> had, if we may believe himſelf, yea he began to expreſs ſome acts of it, when with his uſual boldneſs, and fervency of Spirit, he man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully drew his ſword in his maſters quarrel. And yet all this proved nothing but a piece of gallantry, an heat, and bravery in our Apoſtle; he had never forcaſted with himſelf, what might enſue, and his vain glorious reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion included a thouſand particulars, which he was not aware off. For ſee how ſoon the Scene is changed. This great Champion of our Saviour is of a ſudden daunted, and ſtricken out of countenance, he that had his name from a <hi>rock,</hi> is immediatly <hi>ſhaken like a reed;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo ſolemn an engagement, and proteſtation not to forſake Chriſt, tho every one elſe ſhould, he is driven from this ſteadfaſtneſs by the voice of a ſilly Damſel, and was the firſt of all, that not only diſown'd, but even with oaths and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95120:8"/>imprecations deny'd, and forſwore his maſter. Surely this was written for our admonition, and left upon record for a ſtanding example of the deceitfulneſs of our own hearts, the frailty of the greateſt paſſions, the folly of preſuming upon our own ſtrength, that <hi>every man at his beſt estate is altogether vanity,</hi> and that the deepeſt thoughts, and moſt adviſed conſultations are all little enough to ſupport and ſtrengthen our reſolutions.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly and more particularly it is required for the forming a fixt, and ſteady reſolution, that the mind be prepar'd for all events, and arm'd, and fortify'd againſt the worſt of evils, that can befal us. To which purpoſe it will highly contribute, if we make theſe things, as much as we can, actuall, and preſent to our thoughts, and ſuppoſe our ſelves at our firſt ſetting out, already incompaſt with all thoſe difficulties, and diſtreſſes, which we may reaſonably expect will afterwards aſſault, and ſet upon us in our Journey.</p>
            <p>Under theſe apprehenſions it was, that the prophet <hi>David</hi> here made, and continued, and renued his reſolutions of ſtedfaſt adherence to his God. <hi>The wicked</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have laid a ſnare for me, yet I erred not from thy precepts, v.</hi> 110, and 109. <hi>My ſoul is continually in my hands</hi> i.e. every moment ready to be ſnatcht out of them, <hi>yet do I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95120:9"/>not forget thy law.</hi> Thus <hi>v.</hi> 87. <hi>they had almoſt conſumed me upon earth, but I forſook not thy Commandments</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 157. <hi>Many are now my perſecutors, and enemies, yet do I not decline from thy teſtimonies</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely he that deliberately, and entirely devotes himſelf to the ſervice of religion, has forcaſt with himſelf the worſt that can happen, and ſo is by that means ready and prepared with an undaunted reſolution to encounter it. He has conſidered what it is, and ſo is well enough contented to deny himſelf, to renounce the friendſhip of the world, to ſmile upon the face of danger, to <hi>hate Father and mother, brother and ſiſter, lands and poſſeſsions</hi> and even <hi>life</hi> it ſelf rather than part with that, without which even life it ſelf is not worthy the enjoying.</p>
            <p>Through <hi>honour and diſhonour,</hi> through <hi>evil report,</hi> and <hi>good report,</hi> through a red ſea, and a wilderneſs, through watchings, and faſtings, through afflictions and diſtreſſes, through dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and diſcouragements, he will preſs forward towards the prize of his high calling, and will neither be byaſt from his mark by the flattering conſiderations of the world, nor forc't from it by any terrors, or ſufferings whatſoever.</p>
            <p>He that frames his reſolution with this proſpect, will not ſo eaſily fail in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, he foreſees what he muſt truſt to, he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95120:9"/>knows the worſt of it, he will not have his arms to ſeek, when the enemy is upon him, and ſo is not likely to be, ſurprized with ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den aſſaults, or to be beaten off, and worſted in the conflict. And this is the method, which our Saviour took with his Diſciples, and alſo with others, who offer'd themſelves to be his proſelites. He acquaints them before hand what they muſt look for, in divers places plainly tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, that they muſt expect in this world the worſt of temporal evils, that ſo they might be enabled to meet them with courage and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and habituate their minds to entertain them. We read <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.19. that a certain Scribe ſtruck with admiration of our Saviours miracles was very earneſt to become one of his Diſciples. He comes to him with a very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion of his Zeal to ſerve him, <hi>Maſter I will follow thee whereſoever thou goeſt.</hi> Our Saviour, to try what grounds he had for ſuch a confident reſolution, informs him how mean, and contemptible his worldly condition was, <hi>the Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the Air have neſts, but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head.</hi> He bad him think of this, and then reſolve what to doe. We do not indeed read what became of him afterwards, but from the ſilence of the Evangeliſts it is very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he ſlunk away in the Croud, as fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95120:10"/>and diſappointed in his mighty hopes, and expectations. And thus our Saviour fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deals with thoſe, whom he had choſen for his Diſciples. <hi>In the world ye ſhall have tribulation. Joh.</hi> 16.33. <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my name ſake, Mark</hi> 13.13. And if this ſhould not alwaies happen to be their lot, yet the conſtant reſolution to undergoe this heavy task was abſolutly neceſſary. For <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.24. <hi>The Diſciple is not above his Master, nor the ſervant above his Lord. It is enough for the Diſciple that he be as his Master, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant as his Lord. And if they have called the maſter of the houſe Belzebub, how much more ſhall they call them of his houſhold,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 36. <hi>He that taketh not up his Croſs, and followeth after me, is not worthy of me.</hi> And leaſt we ſhould think theſe to be only Counſels of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or particular injunctions, as ſome doe, and not neceſſary precepts, to which all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are obliged, our Saviour directs the ſame leſſon to the great multitude, that follow'd him <hi>Luke</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>And there went great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes with him, and he turned, and ſaid unto them If any man come unto me, and doth not hate his father and mother, wife, children, and brethren, and ſiſters, yea and his own life, he cannot be my Diſciple; and whoſoever doth not bear his Croſs, and come after me, he cannot be Diſciple.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95120:10"/>
            <p>The neceſſity of this method, for the fixing a thorow reſolution, he there more fully illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in two appoſite compariſons; he that will <hi>build a tower</hi> muſt firſt be able to compute, and calculate the charges, and the means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray them, otherwiſe to begin, being unable to make an end, is to make himſelf ridiculous to the world of ſcorners for an unadviſed and fooliſh undertaking. A Prince likewiſe that will go to war, muſt firſt ſit down and conſult with himſelf, whether he be ſufficiently provided with all neceſſaries for the expedition, <hi>whether he be able with ten thouſand to meet him that cometh againſt him with twenty thouſand.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it will be better for him to keep peace, if he have it, or, being engaged, to get it if he can. For elſe he will thruſt an advantage into the hands of his enemy, and procure nothing but diſgrace and poverty to himſelf.</p>
            <p>The concluſion of there two parables our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour repeats again, v. 33. <hi>So likewiſe whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be of you, that forſaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my diſciple,</hi> i.e. he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to hold out, and ſo had better never pretend to ſuch a glorious profeſſion. The ſum of which ſhort inference is briefly this, that ere we can upon ſure grounds reſolve upon a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious courſe, or ſafely proclaim war againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, it will be neceſſary to make over all intereſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95120:11"/>in our lives, or whatſoever is near and dear to us, to love all perſons and things leſs than our Saviour, which will then appear, when we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer none of them to make us deſert his ſervice, or flinch from our purpoſes, and reſolutions to obey him.</p>
            <p>When the young man in the Goſpel came to Chriſt to ſhew him the way to eternal life, our Saviour replies, <hi>ſell all that thou haſt, and give to the poor, and thou ſhalt have treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and come, and follow me.</hi> Upon this, ſays the text, <hi>he went away ſorrowful for he had great poſseſſions.</hi> This ſoon diſcovered the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and inſufficiency of his pretended reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he had only cheated his own ſoul with a bare appearance of religion, which was not truly ſeated in his heart, for his heart was in his treaſure, and ſo he could not endure to think of ſelling it, and entring upon a poor, and perſecuted religion.</p>
            <p>And this was the caſe of a great many more beſides him, and has been the cauſe of many fearful ſhipwracks of faith and a good conſcience to this day. This temper our Saviour has repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the <hi>ſtony ground,</hi> in the parable of the ſower <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. Men may receive the doctrine of the Goſpel into their hearts with joy, but for want of a good ſoil, where it may take deep root, for want of an entire reſolution to bear
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95120:11"/>whatſoever the Goſpel requires of them, they laſt but a little while. For tho they ſeem to thrive, and flouriſh for a while, yet aſſoon as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution ariſes becauſe of the Goſpel, when any chargeable duty is exacted of them, immediately they are offended, i.e. galled and diſcouraged from any further progreſs: which notes unto us, that when ſecular intereſt outweighs duty, when Chriſt is forſaken becauſe of perſecution, then that imaginary reſolution, which men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made ſhew of, was not founded in the true motives of religion, which are the ſame at all times, nor upon any other ground, but ſuch as is contrary to perſecution, i. e. their ſecular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and advantages. And then no wonder if the change of their intereſt alter their reſolutions, and the ſame motive, which makes men zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> be at another time of equal force for the calves of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But a true Chriſtian reſolution is built upon a fixt and immoveable foundation, that has no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon times or ſeaſons, upon fair or fowl weather, and makes a man uniform and conſtant in his courſe, whatever betides him, the ſame in a ſtorm as in the Sun ſhine, he will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the word with joy,</hi> though it be alſo <hi>in much affliction.</hi> And ſurely that man much undervalues God, and ſo cannot reſolve to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95120:12"/>ſerve him as he ought, who deems any thing comparable to him, or fit to be conſidered, when he comes in competition. He that holds his body dear (ſays the Philoſopher) muſt count ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty but little worth, and it is impoſſible that a man ſhould earneſtly fix his thoughts or ſettle his reſolutions upon the purſuit of things above, unleſs he firſt wholly take them off from all things here below, and be indifferently affected towards all outward comforts, and complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. The whole of this conſideration is ſumm'd up in that comprehenſive advice of the wiſe man, <hi>My ſon, when thou comeſt to ſerve the Lord, prepare thy ſoul for temptation count the coſt,</hi> as our Saviour bids thee, forethink the worſt of it, conſider well what thou wilt do, when things come to the puſh, and this will be a great help with Gods grace and aſſiſtance, to plant ſuch a firm reſolution of piety and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the bottom of thy heart, as ſhall enable thee to devour all difficulties, to break through all diſcouragements, and to hold out manfully, till thou haſt finiſht thy courſe to the end, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the fierceſt oppoſitions thou ſhalt meet with by the way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is requiſite to a well grounded reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that it be entire and comprehenſive of our whole duty, not taken up in a humour againſt this or that particular ſin, but equally ſet againſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95120:12"/>all known ſins, and uniformly bent to walk in all the good ways of God, without any exception or reſervation. <hi>David</hi> is our example here in ſeveral places of this <hi>Pſalm.</hi> Thus v. 101. <hi>I have refrained my ſelf from every evil way, that I might keep thy word.</hi> and v. 6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy commandments.</hi> and v. 128. <hi>Therefore I eſteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right, and I hate every falſe way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Jews had entertained a corrupt notion among them, that God at the laſt day would put our good works and bad into the balance, and according to the heavier ſcale determine our condition in the world to come, ſo that if the moſt part of a mans actions were holy and juſt, though in others he ſinn'd often, yet the greater ingredient should prevail, and the bigger num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his obſervances of the law, ſhould out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh the leſſer of his deviations from it. Nay ſome went a great deal further, and taught, that if a man obſerved but one command well, it was not abſolutely neceſſary, that he ſhould keep the reſt, and ſo left men at liberty to take to themſelves what part of duty they pleaſed, and let the reſt alone.</p>
            <p>But ſurely a truely religious reſolution is founded upon a general, and univerſal reaſon, which takes in all our concerns, and equally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95120:13"/>extends it ſelf to all ſins, and duties whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And this is one ſure way to diſcover the ſtrength, and ſoundneſs of mens reſolutions in religion. This was the Caſe of <hi>Jehu,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his flouriſhing pretences for a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row reformation. He made great ſhew for a while of Zeal for God, and his worſhip, and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab</hi> muſt needs go along with him to ſee it, <hi>Come ſee my Zeal for the Lord of hoſts;</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed <hi>Baal,</hi> and his worſhip, out of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry couragiouſly: But he preſently diſcovered the ſelfiſh principle that he was acted by, For he gave way to the Calves no leſs abominable in the ſight of God, and cleav'd to the ſin of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin</p>
            <p>The like was the Caſe of <hi>Herod, Mark</hi> 6.20. He ſtood in ſome awe of, <hi>John, knowing him to be a juſt man, and Holy,</hi> and becauſe he would be eſteemed religious, and would ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect him, he heard him often, and upon his motion did many good things, and it is like enough that he reformed many things amiſs, which <hi>John</hi> found fault with, either in his Court, or in himſelf. So fair a teſtimony does the Evangeliſt give him of many ſpecious perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances in matters of religion. But no ſooner was he touch't in that tender point in his <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodias,</hi> in his darling, his reigning ſin, but the mask of a ſudden falls off, and he preſently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95120:13"/>the baſe and corrupt ends of his former zeal, and reformation.</p>
            <p>There are many partial principles and ends in men, which will oblige them to abſtain from ſome ſins, and be very careful in ſome duties, as ſhame of the world, the fear of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhment, and the hope of temporal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the power of cuſtom, the influence of education, their particular temper, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, the affectation of popularity and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ingenuity, the terrors of an affrighted conſcience, and even the antipathy of ſins, and inconſiſtency, that is often found between one ſin, and another. But if in the mean time there be no Care nor conſcience of other ſins, where there appeareth no influence from theſe and the like conſiderations, the principle is ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, we are as much under the univerſal reign, and dominion of ſin, as ever, and are far removed from ſuch a reſolution, as will prove a ſolid permanent foundation of vertue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For it is founded barely in particular reaſons, and ſo has no more ſtrength than is derived from them.</p>
            <p>But a true reſolution is uniform, abſolute and univerſal, free from all by and ſiniſter reſpects, all concealed, and hypocritical reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It enables a man to abſtain from ſin out of an entire hatred of An as ſuch, and to yield
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95120:14"/>obedience to the law of God, out of a ſincere eſteem of the authority of the Legiſlator. And therefore he cannot be perſwaded to pick and chuſe what particular duties to obſerve, ſuch as may be moſt for his own advantage. For he looks upon the whole law of God as one, and the ſame rule, impartial, conſtant and unvariable, and that it was given us by God to direct our actions, and not to be bow'd, and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to the luſts, and intereſts of men.</p>
            <p>Satan is well aware of this, and ſo is not much concern'd to ſee men obſervant of many duties, ſo long as he holds poſſeſſion by one ſingle ſin. This is enough at any time to maintain his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and ſecure his intereſt in the Soul. He knows well enough, that the cheriſhing of one luſt, will corrupt and vitiate all other laudable performances; that one <hi>Achan</hi> could bring a Curſe upon the whole Congregation; that one ſin is enough to ruine us; or if it were not, yet while he holds that one faſt, he will quickly make way for a whole Legion to enter in.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhown, what things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for the forming a religious reſolution. It remains that I add a word or two, of what great uſe and moment it is in the buſineſs of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>And 1ſt. a reſolution thus framed will have a powerful influence over the whole Soul to keep
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95120:14"/>it fixt, and intent upon its duty, to engage all the faculties thereof to proceed immediately to act according to their reſpective offices, and apply, and put forth their forces with vigor and conſtancy for the attainment of that end, which it has fixt, and determin'd to its ſelf.</p>
            <p>As we ſee in other reſolutions, when a man reſolvedly intends his profit, pleaſure, advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or whatever ſtate in this life how doth it ſet the whole man at work, 'twill employ all his thoughts, his cares, his endeavors, 'tis the buſineſs of his parts, his ſtudy, his whole life to purſue it, he ſticks at nothing that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, or further his deſign, he ſpares no pains, neglects no means that may tend to compaſs it, all the powers of Soul and Body, yield a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obedience to this commanding reſolution.</p>
            <p>The like effect we ſhould perceive in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of religion, if men were but as earneſt, reſolute, and intent upon it, as upon their worldly advantages and ſatisfactions. For were our wills fixt to it, did our affections concenter in it, how eager ſhould we be in the purſuit, how lively and vigorous in our actions, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances. for then it would be nothing more but following the natural tendences of our own Souls, to act ſuitably to our tempers and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; our duty would become our choice, and our delight, and 'twould be force, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95120:15"/>to be drawn from it. So that if once we are arriv'd thus far, that virtue is become the matter of our firm purpoſes and reſolutions; when the heart is ſet upon it, it will ſweeten all our Cares, make all our labours eaſy and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, breath life, and Spirit into our works and actions. For it has won the principle that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them all, as the ſpring of a watch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts a motion to all the wheels of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17. we find this to be the great argument which <hi>Moſes</hi> preſſes upon the men of <hi>Iſrael. Thou haſt voucht the Lord this day to be thy God, and to walk in his waves, and to keep his ſtatutes, his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his Judgments, and to hearken to his voice.</hi> He thought this a mighty enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the obligation they lay under, that they had then reſolved upon it, they had plight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their fidelity, and engaged their truth to God ſo, that the very ſhame of being falſe to ſuch an avowed ſolemn reſolution ſhould oblige them, even in point of honour, to make it good.</p>
            <p>For this is evident, that reſolution with its own ſtrength would be able to effect that, for want whereof the greateſt part of mankind prove ſo often ſucceſſeſs in their undertakings. We ſee by experience the force of it in other things that it attempts, how it goes through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt greater difficulties than the ways of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95120:15"/>are encumbred with. And we may be ſure in the preſent Caſe, that it will proſper in the thing it undertakes, and unleſs men have a mind to be conquered, and baſely deſert their reſolutions, they cannot miſcarry.</p>
            <p>This will prove an effectual remedy againſt the main miſtakes, errors, and imperfections of our lives, ſecure us from unſettledneſs, and flit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from one thing to another, and keep us ſtedfaſt in our duty, fix and faſten us to our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It will confirm, ſettle, and ſtabliſh the fick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leneſs and ſlipperineſs of our hearts, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this are very various and changeable, and like a ſhip without ballaſt, ready to be overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with every wind that blows againſt it. It will preſerve us from being faint and weary, when we meet with any unexpected obſtacles in <hi>run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the race that is ſet before us.</hi> It will make our converſation all of apiece, breed a conſtancy, and unſwaydneſs in our lives and actions, make us firm <hi>and immoveable</hi> in the practiſe of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to continue and perſevere in our Courſe, to add to <hi>our faith vertue,</hi> — and ſo onward, to <hi>go from ſtrength to ſtrength, until we appear before God in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2d. A firm and well ſettled reſolution, will prove a powerful preſervative againſt Satans temptations. It will either diſcourage and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten them, or elſe enable us to repel them.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95120:16"/>The Devil hath but ſmall hope to ſeduce, and miſlead a reſolved Chriſtian: when he diſcerns men in earneſt to ſtand upon their guard, watch to avoid all opportunities and occaſions, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and fortify againſt him, there he will not ſtay to receive a baffle and diſapointment, he will leave off ſoliciting, when he ſees 'tis to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And ſurely if we ſurvey, and ſum up all the forces which the Devil, the world, and the moſt dangerous enemy, our own fleſh, are able to raiſe againſt us, all means and devices, ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems and policies, whereby they continually attempt to abuſe and ruine us, there is force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in a holy reſolution to fruſtrate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat them all. For it is not here as in other wars, where the braveſt gallantry and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be ſometimes overpowred and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. But in our conflict with our Spiritual enemies, we can never be conquered, as long as we hold our reſolutions, unleſs we make a cowardly and diſhonourable retreat, or ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conſent to our own overthrow. For let the Devil do his worſt, let him diſcourage or allure, aſſault and ſtorm us, we can never be vanquiſhed, if we will not yield. Temptation puts on its ſtrength according to the frame and temper of our wills, and as long as we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, all the Divels in hell cannot force us
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95120:16"/>upon a ſin. Temptations may knock at our hearts, but they cannot enter, unleſs we open the doors, and let them in.</p>
            <p>When ever therefore thou findeſt thy ſelf tempted to the commiſſion of a ſin, eſpecially thy boſom, thy beloved ſin, the ſin that <hi>does ſo eaſily beſet thee,</hi> which thy Soul delights in, be aſſured that it comes upon Satans errand, do not treat with it, but call up all thy former Vows, Oaths, Covenants, and reſolutions ſay, <hi>I have ſworn, and am ſtedfaſtly purpoſed</hi> to live in obedience to my maker. <hi>How ſhall I do this great wickedneſs, and ſin against God. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from me ye wicked, for I will keep the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of my God.</hi> I am engaged by a ſolemn vow, the ſtrongeſt bond I can think of, and have taken a Sacrament upon it, never to admit that into my heart whereby I have been formerly betray'd.</p>
            <p>If the devil further endeavor to fright thee with the Croſſes and reproaches, that thou art hereby expoſed to, that thou wilt probably ſuffer many things not very grateful, and pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fleſh and blood, ſay, 'tis no more then I look't for, the Croſs is no ſcandal to me. I have ſworn to <hi>fight manfully under Chriſts banner, and to continue his faithful ſouldier, and ſervant, to my lives end.</hi> I know well enough upon what terms I liſted my ſelf in his Service, and I'le
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95120:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>not deſert it whatſoever ſhall befal me. Theſe conſiderations, with the aſſiſtance of Gods Grace, will by degrees work thee up into <hi>St. Pauls</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that <hi>neither life, nor death, things preſent, nor things to come, ſhall be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thee from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Collect for the 2d. Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day after Epiphany</note>
               <hi>And thou O God that knoweſt us to be ſet in the midſt of ſo many, and great dangers, that by reaſon of the frailty of our nature we cannot alwaies ſtand upright, Grant to us ſuch strength, and protection, as may ſupport us in all dangers, and carry us thro all temptations , thro Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom with the Father, and the Holy Spirit, be all Honour, and Glory World without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
